<resources>
    <string name="app_name">CoronaVirusGuide</string>
    <string name="new_txt1">Any of a family (Coronaviridae) of single-stranded RNA viruses that have a lipid envelope studded with club-shaped projections, infect birds and many mammals including humans, and include the causative agents of MERS and SARS.
    </string>
    <string name="new_txt2">1)Avoid close contact with people who are sick. 2)Avoid touching your eyes, nose, and mouth. 3)Stay home when you are sick. Cover your cough or sneeze with a tissue, then throw the tissue in the trash. 4)Clean and disinfect frequently touched objects and surfaces using a regular household cleaning spray or wipe.</string>
    <string name="new_txt3">Always consult a health care provider or visit a travel health clinic at least 6 weeks before you travel.  When travelling to places near Wuhan, China:  wash your hands frequently with soap and water for at least 20 seconds use alcohol-based hand sanitizer only if soap and water are not available it is a good idea to always keep some with you when you travel eat and drink safely abroad by staying away from raw or undercooked food and meat avoid high-risk areas such as farms, live animal markets and areas where animals may be slaughtered avoid close contact with people who may be sick, especially if they have difficulty breathing or have a fever or cough avoid contact with animals (alive or dead), including pigs, chickens, ducks and wild birds, and items contaminated with their body fluids Visit the travel advice and advisories page for the most up-to-date information on the risk of coronavirus in your travel destination. This information will help you:  be aware of the local situation follow local public health advice</string>
    <string name="new_txt4">Signs and symptoms of infection with the new coronavirus may appear two to 14 days after exposure and can include:  Fever Cough Shortness of breath or difficulty breathing The severity of the new coronavirus symptoms can range from very mild to severe, even death. Although understanding of this disease continues to grow, most people with severe illness have been of an older age or had other significant existing medical conditions. This is similar to what is seen in people who have severe infections with other respiratory illnesses, such as influenza.</string>
    <string name="new_txt5">Contact your doctor right away if you have symptoms of infection with the new coronavirus and you\'ve possibly been exposed to the virus. Tell your doctor if you\'ve recently traveled internationally. Call your doctor ahead to tell him or her about your symptoms and recent travels and possible exposure before you go to your appointment.</string>
    <string name="new_txt6">Risk factors for infection with the new coronavirus appear to include:  Recent travel from or residence in China Close contact with someone who has the new coronavirus — such as when a family member or health care worker takes care of an infected person People who are older or who have other existing medical conditions, such as diabetes and heart disease, may be at higher risk of becoming seriously ill with the new coronavirus. But there is still much unknown about the virus, and the CDC and WHO continue to investigate.</string>
    <string name="new_txt7">कोरोना वायरस (सीओवी) का संबंध वायरस के ऐसे परिवार से है, जिसके संक्रमण से जुकाम से लेकर सांस लेने में तकलीफ जैसी समस्या हो सकती है. इस वायरस को पहले कभी नहीं देखा गया है. इस वायरस का संक्रमण दिसंबर में चीन के वुहान में शुरू हुआ था. डब्लूएचओ के मुताबिक, बुखार, खांसी, सांस लेने में तकलीफ इसके लक्षण हैं. अब तक इस वायरस को फैलने से रोकने वाला कोई टीका नहीं बना है.</string>
    <string name="new_txt8">इसके संक्रमण के फलस्वरूप बुखार, जुकाम, सांस लेने में तकलीफ, नाक बहना और गले में खराश जैसी समस्या उत्पन्न होती हैं. यह वायरस एक व्यक्ति से दूसरे व्यक्ति में फैलता है. इसलिए इसे लेकर बहुत सावधानी बरती जा रही है. यह वायरस दिसंबर में सबसे पहले चीन में पकड़ में आया था. इसके दूसरे देशों में पहुंच जाने की आशंका जताई जा रही है.</string>
    <string name="new_txt9">स्‍वास्‍थ्‍य मंत्रालय ने कोरोना वायरस से बचने के लिए दिशानिर्देश जारी किए हैं. इनके मुताबिक, हाथों को साबुन से धोना चाहिए. अल्‍कोहल आधारित हैंड रब का इस्‍तेमाल भी किया जा सकता है. खांसते और छीकते समय नाक और मुंह रूमाल या टिश्‍यू पेपर से ढककर रखें. जिन व्‍यक्तियों में कोल्‍ड और फ्लू के लक्षण हों उनसे दूरी बनाकर रखें. अंडे और मांस के सेवन से बचें. जंगली जानवरों के संपर्क में आने से बचें. चीन में इस वायरस के चलते पर्यटकों की संख्या घट सकती है. इसका सीधा असर चीन की अर्थव्यवस्था पर पड़ेगा. पहले ही चीन की अर्थव्यवस्था सुस्ती के दौर में है. कई देशों ने अपने नागरिकों से चीन नहीं जाने के लिए कहा है. कई देशों ने वुहान से आने वाले लोगों पर भी प्रतिबंध लगा दिया है. रूस ने चीन के साथ अपने पूर्वी बॉर्डर को भी बंद कर दिया है. लगभग 18 साल पहले सार्स वायरस से भी ऐसा ही खतरा बना था. 2002-03 में सार्स की वजह से पूरी दुनिया में 700 से ज्यादा लोगों की मौत हुई थी. पूरी दुनिया में हजारों लोग इससे संक्रमित हुए थे. इसका असर आर्थिक गतिविधियों पर भी पड़ा था.</string>
    <string name="new_txt10">विश्व स्वास्थ्य संगठन के मुताबिक, कोरोना वायरस सी-फूड से जुड़ी हुई बीमारी है. यह बीमारी चीन के सी-फूड बाजार से शुरू हुई. डब्लूएचओ के मुताबिक, यह वायरस ऊंट, बिल्ली, चमगादड़ सहित कई पशुओं में फैलने के बाद इंसानों में तेजी से फैल रहा है. कोरोना वायरस से संक्रमित व्यक्ति को सांस की बीमारी होती है और पीड़ित को ठंड लगती है, जो निमोनिया के लक्षण जैसे प्रतीत होते हैं. इस बीच सोशल मीडिया साईट पर एक व्यक्ति ने दावा किया है कि चीन में करीब एक हफ्ते से अस्पताल में भर्ती कोरोना वायरस से संक्रमित एक व्यक्ति का सफलता से इलाज हो चुका है.</string>
    <string name="new_txt11">कोरोना वायरस से संक्रमण से बचाव के लिए संक्रमित लोगों से दूर रहना चाहिए. भीड़ में जाने पर हाथ-मुंह धोना चाहिए, बुखार और खांसी होने पर घरेलू और सामान्य उपचार करने के बजाय तुरंत डॉक्टर से सलाह लेनी चाहिए. अगर आप सी फूड का सेवन करते हैं तो तुरंत उससे बचना चाहिए. कोरोना वायरस का संक्रमण पीड़ित व्यक्ति से हाथ मिलाने से भी हो सकता है.</string>
    <string name="new_txt12">कोरोना वायरस से पीड़ित लोगों का अन्य दवाइयों के साथ इलाज किया जा रहा है. वैज्ञानिक कोरोना वायरस का इलाज और वैक्सीन बनाने का काम कर रहे हैं. रायटर्स की एक रिपोर्ट के मुताबिक चीन इस समय एचआईवी के इलाज में इस्तेमाल होने वाली दवा आलुविया से कोरोना का इलाज करने की कोशिश में जुटा है. डॉक्टर का कहना है कि कोरोना से प्रभावित या संक्रमित व्यक्ति का इलाज विशेषज्ञ की निगरानी में ही कराया जाना चाहिए. आम तौर पर आप सर्दी-जुकाम कम करने के प्राकृतिक उपाय कर कोरोना के संक्रमण पर काफी हद तक काबू पा सकते हैं. इसके लिए रूम ह्युमिडिफायर का उपयोग या गर्म पानी से नहाने जैसे काम किये जा सकते हैं.</string>

</resources>
